Everyone, welcome back.
This is Vishwa Rajkwapalan,
Associate Professor in
Biomedical Sciences.
Today we're going to
talk about continuation
of what we saw in cardiac
cycle part one and
this is on related to
loops, loss and cardiac
output and related
principles and applications
of physiology of the
cardiovascular system.
Okay,
so the session objectives
are to graph the relationship
between cardiac pressures
and volumes using law of
laplace and to recognize
concepts of cardiac output
and stroke volume in a cardiac
cycle and to distinguish
between afterload preload
and frank sterling's law
and factors that regulate
stroke volume and cardiac
output in a cardiac cycle
and then how do you measure
cardiac output using a
couple of methodologies and
then to extrapolate the various
concepts that we studied
that's different phases
the loops and laws and all
those things in a rep
in using representative
cardiovascular pathologies okay
okay let's jump on so so this
is a beating heart I've
shown this figure before
and this beating heart
coincides with the different
phases of the cardiac cycle
and just to refresh that if
it's been a little break
since you watched the first
in a part of this
cardiac cycle.
We have aortic
pressure here, we have
atrial pressure,
ventricular pressure,
we have ventricular
volume, I don't know if
you're seeing my
cursor, let me try this,
okay, ventricular volume,
electrocardiogram,
phonocardiogram, and so on, okay,
all right.
Now this is also something
that you have seen and as
you can see, as you can
see, I think this is not
moving maybe because of the
slideshow limitations but
when you go to slideshow
it should show this moving.
The loop in the bottom,
the volume versus pressure
loop, should coincide with
the different phases of the
cycle above in the upper
part of the figure. Okay,
so we will look in
detail about the
volume versus pressure
curve. We have
already seen the
upper part before.
All right,
There you go, you can see it,
yeah, so as it loops,
you can see,
yes, this is
pressure increasing,
now it's pressure decreasing,
you can correlate with
the different phases of
the cardiac cycle, alright.
Now here,
what is law of Laplace,
law of Laplace relates to
ventricular pressure and its
relationship with the wall
tension and the radius now
imagine ventricular chamber
and you look at from top
to bottom in the sense that
it's like a circle now
okay imagine it's a circle
and that's the circle you're
seeing here this circle
okay and when you cut the
ventricle um uh the middle the
transverse you know section
you can see this and the
the pressure exerted is
proportional to the wall
tension in the walls of the
left ventricular wall and
then the radius of the
chamber or the diameter or the
radius of the chamber okay
more specifically um the
rest of the formula we will
see in the next slide um
but what i want to point
out here is uh in the x-axis
is left ventricular volume
y-axis left ventricular
pressure um mitral valve
opens in this phase okay here
mitral valve opens mitral
valve closes aortic valve
opens aortic valve closes
Remember in the cardiac vigorous
diagram, we showed in a
different format where
these valves open and close.
Try to imagine that, okay?
But let's focus here.
As the left ventricular
volume increases, what
does that mean? As the
left ventricular volume
increases, that means
the left ventricle is
relaxing and dilating.
And it reaches to a
point where there is end
diastolic volume, which
I said I will explain.
Endo-historic volume is
the point where maximum
amount of volume the
ventricle has taken.
At that point, the
mitral valve closes.
So it's not receiving any
more blood from the left
atrium at this point. What
happens after this? It's
only pressure that's going
to build up for preparing
for the ejection. This is
iso-olimetric contraction.
After iso-olimetric
contraction, the aortic valve
opens and then blood just
pushes, gets gushed out of the
left ventricle. This is rapid
ejection phase, remember,
and this is reduced ejection
phase of left ventricle.
These are three phases
of the ventricle system.
Isolumetric contraction,
rapid ejection,
reduced ejection.
And then the aortic
valve closes.
Right after it closes,
immediately the pressure falls.
Pressure falls, but iso
-volumetric relaxation. It
relaxes, but it's not receiving
the blood yet because both
the valves are closed. Look,
aortic valve is closed,
and then mitral valve is
also closed. But it's only
at this point of pressure,
the mitral valve will open.
At a high pressure,
it will not open. It
should not open. When it
goes down almost close
to zero, not exactly
zero, but close to zero,
it will open up. Once
it opens up, then it's
ready to receive the
next cycle of blood.
This point is called end
systolic volume at the end
of systole. And this is
end of diastole. Things
you need to remember. And
remember this thing, this
thing is called stroke
volume, right? This point
to this point, which means
at this point to this
point, approximately from
50 ml of blood till about
120 ml of blood, the
difference of about 70, right?
50, 100, 20, 20, yes.
This is stroke volume.
In one stroke, what is
the amount of volume
that is being
ejected out of the
ventricle? That is
called the stroke volume.
Alright, with that
we will move on.
Again, you are seeing the
same slide on the right,
but on the left you are
seeing what is end-diastolic
volume. volume, it is also
referred to as preload
and afterload is proportional
to arterial pressure.
We will talk about
afterload and preload later.
But here what you
need to understand
is this wall stress formula.
Again, this is a more
proper, more complete law
of Laplace which states
that wall tension is
proportional to the
pressure times radius for
thin walled spheres or
cylinders. Therefore,
wall stress, this is wall
stress, is proportional
to wall tension, wall
tension is P times R,
okay, wall tension is P times R
divided by H, okay,
let's quickly see,
yes,
you saw wall tension
is equals, P equals T
by R, if you rewrite
the formula, T equals P
times R, okay, and P
times R is wall tension
divided by H thickness,
that is wall stress.
Now wall stress is the
primary determinant
of how much oxygen the
heart muscle consumes.
By keeping the ventricular
radius relatively small
and the wall adequately
thick, the normal heart
operates efficiently without
excessive energy expenditure,
okay, hope this is
clear so far you need to
understand in the loop and
remember questions may come
related to the pressure
volume loop and remember
the formula as well different
formulas we won't do
too many formulas but
there are some formula that
you need to remember and
understand remember this
is stroke volume mitral
valve opening here closing
here these things you
need to remember draw hand
draw or drawing an app or
anywhere notepad anywhere
this go and practice so
you really get it deeper
within. This is the period
of ejection, this is
isolumetric contraction,
this is isolumetric
relaxation, and this is the
period of filling, right?
This is the diastolic
filling, okay? Let's move on.
Okay, now let's clear this
away. Now if you look at
patients with diabetic,
dilated cardiomyopathy,
excuse me, they have big
heart, you see that, right?
On the left you see normal
size heart and the right
you see cardiomyopathic
heart which is in heart
failure what are the
characteristic changes you are
seeing one of course it's
dilated what is dilated
literally everything is
dilated all the four chambers
are dilated look at the
left ventricle comparatively
the chamber diameter is
increased right it's what we
are talking about in the
laplace law we saw radius
radius is half of the diameter
the entire diameter is
this so it's going to it's
going to increase compared
to this and then look at the
atrial look at the atrial
look at the right ventricular
diameter okay what else
do you see abnormal here
thickness right you see how
this is optimal thickness
if we say this is optimal
thickness look at the thickness
it has thinned okay it
is thinned here and so the
ventricular thinning is
one characteristic of some
of the cardiomyopathies okay
which means it is not able
to generate enough amount
of pressure that wall tension
and the pressure it is
not able to generate so
that means the that is not
adequate you know amount of
energy for the heart to you
know use to push the
blood out okay so this is
something important that you
need to understand and on the
top is the x-ray you're
seeing similar thing all right
let's move on to understand
the similar situations
in using different other
measures ventricular pressure
volume relationships why
do we talk about all these
things one to understand the
physiology two to understand
the clinical relevance and
three from the perspective
of exams right not just
your school exams but
also board exams these think
these questions do come
you can see in practice
exam questions these kind of
things do come. So we want
to prepare you adequately so
that you are well exposed
to some of these concepts.
Okay,
let's move on.
Ventricle pressure volume
relation. Two things
you need to remember.
One is ESPVR, other is
EDPVR. These are the
two major things in this
slide you need to know.
All right, what are they?
EDPVR is end diastolic
pressure volume relationship.
And what is it? It's
a curve. You see this
is the curve? Yeah, it
is a curve that defines
the passive stiffness and
compliance of the ventricle.
Again, EDPVR is a
curve that defines the
passive stiffness and
compliance of the ventricle.
For example, in a
pathological conditions
like ventricular hypertrophy,
ventriculars are
abnormally thickened.
When can that happen?
Hypertrophic
cardiomyopathy. Okay, that's
one example where it
is extraordinarily
thickened. There are
many other conditions.
Severe blood pressure,
severe hypertension.
situations like that what
happens then the ventricle
is stiffer and less
compliant less compliant and
therefore the slope of the
filling curve is increased
so what happened how
will the curve look like
the curve will go towards
the left okay it may go
like this or even more so
it shifts to the left okay
I'll clear this away so
curve shifts to the left
in terms of when EDPVR is
it's upward and steeper
okay so that's example
ventricular hypertrophy
ventricle is stiffer and less
compliant now what is the
contrary that can happen
in a case of dilated
cardiomyopathy we just saw
a patient some images in the
previous slide dilated
cardiomyopathy or in some valve
disease a dilated ventricle
has higher passive
compliance and therefore the
slope of the filling curve
is reduced so it shifts to
the right okay and right
and flatter okay so this
is something you need to
remember two things that can
happen it can go this way
or that way two example
conditions I've said okay
let's move on again this is
the loop that we saw before
pv loop volume and pressure
loop, stroke volume,
mitral valve closing,
aortic opening,
aortic closing,
mitral valve opening,
and this is isovolumetric
contraction,
isovolumetric relaxation,
and so on. Okay,
let's look at what
is ESPBR, n-systolic
pressure volume
relationship. What is it?
All right,
n-systolic pressure volume
relationship is a maximal
pressure that can be developed
by the ventricle at any
left ventricular volume again
it is the maximal pressure
that can be developed by
the ventricle at any left
ventricular volume all
right what is the maximal
pressure at see under in the
x-axis is again volume and
y-axis is pressure right
in a in a situation and it
represents the ionotropic
state ionotropic state is a
contractility state of contractility
what is the contractile
state of the ventricle
is it poor or is it good
or is it normal this is
normal okay control control is
the you know the normal
healthy patient heart loop
control is the broken black
line okay if the patient's
ventricle is poor heart attack
or heart failure or many
other conditions where the
heart is not functioning
or not ejecting properly
then the contractility will
go down so what happens to
this entire loop the entire
loop will move towards the
right which means the espvr
curve will move towards
the right this is all you
need to know when the contract
rate is high for instance
in the case of hypothyroidism
or maybe in anemia to
high output conditions
contractility will increase
so the espvr shifts to the
left okay these are the things
that you need to remember.
And there can be other
conditions too, but these
are two key things at this
stage that should be good
for you to understand. This
is controlled ESPVR, when
contractility is poor if it
shifts to the right, and it
is exaggerated if it shifts
to the left. Again ESPVR is
the maximal pressure that
can be developed by the
ventricle at any left
ventricular volume, and it
represents the inotropic state.
Alright,
in the interest of
time we are moving on.
Stroke volume and cardiac
output. I introduced
this concept in the
loop. What is stroke
volume? It is the
amount of blood that is
injected by the heart in
every single heartbeat.
That's the stroke
volume and what is it?
Mathematically it is the
difference between end
diastolic volume and end
systolic volume in milliliters.
And we saw it's about 120
and 50 approximately and
it could range to 70 ml
plus or minus. Cardiac
output, if you multiply that
by heart rate, that's it.
This is in ml per beat
and this is in beats
per minute, so cardiac
output is cancelling
the beats, it's
milliliters per minute.
And as an example, if the
stroke volume is
70 or maybe 80,
the heart rate, let's assume
the heart rate is 72, and
multiply this, 5.7 liters
per minute. That's average,
but again, cardiac output
can go high, can go low,
right? but this is somewhere
a decent number all right
let's move on now the question
is about how are we going
to measure because it's not
straightforward it's not
easy heart rate all right
you can touch the pulse and
measure the heart rate
right you all know how to
measure the pulse rate and
pulse rate and the heart rate
you can do it by EKG you
can do it by you know bunch
of the ways but output is
not that easy to measure it's
not straightforward you need
some some other some more
elaborate measurements. There
are a couple of methods.
One fundamental principle
is Fick principle. What's
Fick principle? Fick principle
states that in a steady
state the oxygen leaving
the lungs per unit volume
via the pulmonary veins they
equal the oxygen entering
the lungs via the mixed
venous blood and respiration.
Again if the oxygen
leaving the lungs
via the pulmonary veins,
it must equal the oxygen
entering the lungs via
the mixed venous blood. So
the formula is oxygen
absorbed per minute by the
lungs divided by arteriovenous
oxygen difference.
The difference is arterial
and venous. This is
venous right side, this
is arterial left side. The
difference is 200 minus 160
and then 200 minus 160 is
what? You get a 40, and
the oxygen utilized is
about 200 in this example.
So 200 away by 40, it will
come down to 5 liters
per minute, back to close
to what we saw before,
right? 5 liters per minute.
All right, that's one method.
Let's look at the other
method. The other method is
indicator dilution method.
What's indicator dilution? So
it's a small amount of
indicator, such as a dye, a
colored dye, is used. it's
injected into a large systemic
vein that enters into
preferably the right atrium.
Okay, femoral vein or a
brachial vein, whatever
they use in a given
laboratory. They inject in the
patient and then it goes
inside the venous system.
So this indicator passes
rapidly through the right
side of the heart, then it
goes to the blood vessels of
the lungs, then through
the left side of the heart,
and finally it reaches the
systemic arterial system.
arteries the concentration
of the dye is then
recorded okay this is the
concentration of dye you can
see is recorded using in
the peripheral arteries
one of the peripheral
arteries radial whatever
they do and then a curve
is generated in the figure
a dye for example a cardio
green dye can be used
so how do we do this briefly
in the top recording you
see that none of the dye
passed into the arterial tree
until about three seconds
it didn't pass and then it
starts passing okay and then
suddenly it shoots up right
you start with the five
milligrams cardio green dye
and suddenly it is detected
okay at about six to seven
seconds it peaks right
maximizes and then following
that the concentration falls
rapidly right it suddenly
falls rapidly but it
doesn't touch the bottom this
is the bottom but it doesn't
it stagnates there right
why take a moment pause the
video and think and then
come back the answer is it
is because before the
concentration reached zero some
of the dye had already
circulated all the way through
some of peripheral systemic
vessels and returned through
the heart for a second
time that that means it's
recirculated and it goes on
okay it gets recirculated and
recirculated is which
means it's not hitting the
bottom so the dye concentration
in the artery began to
rise again now mathematically
how do you measure this
is the formula okay cardiac
output is milligrams of dye
injected we already know
which is 5 milligrams times
60 divided by average
concentration of the dye in each
ml of blood for the duration
of the curve which would
be I think in this case 0
.0025 okay in this example
and when you multiply this
by the duration is 12 seconds
right if you look at the
curve it's about 12 seconds
and then if you look at the
bottom figure here there
is a delay it takes longer
time right it takes longer
time the curve is too deep
which means if the diet
takes longer time to come
back than a normal patient
which means the heart is not
functioning optimally for
it to come back so when
measure the cardiac output the
chances are the the time
point is in the bottom is
increased which means the
cardiac output is likely reduced
okay so that is how it works
okay moving on I wanted
to add another technique
called thermodilution
thermodilution is another
method using swan-gans catheter
in this it's a more realistic
and practically used
method here a thermistor tipped
catheter is inserted into
a peripheral vein into the
pulmonary artery and a cold
saline solution of known
temperature and volume is
injected into the right atrium
from a proximal catheter
port and the solution
mixes with the blood as it
passes through the ventricle
into the PA pulmonary artery
and thus cooling the blood
so the blood temperature
is measured using the
thermistor at the catheter tip
which now sits within the
pulmonary artery and the change
in the blood temperature
is recorded as it flows
over the thermistor surface
and the magnitude of the
decrease in temperature
depends on the volume of blood
that mixes with the solution
which in turn depends on
the cardiac output and thus
the cardiac output is measured
okay so this is another
technique you can keep in
your mind all right moving
on regulation of heart rate
and stroke volume and cardiac
output. Heart rate can
be changed by a bunch of
different factors including
sympathetic and
parasympathetic stimulation.
If the heart rate increases,
stroke volume decreases.
When heart rate increases,
When stroke volume decreases
and why does that happen?
Because it tries to balance
the cardiac output so that
when heart rate increases
too much cardiac output should
not shoot up suddenly so
much because optimal
amount of blood needs to be
circulating in the body or the
heart now on the other hand
if the heart rate decreases
the opposite can happen
but in extreme high heart
rates like it reaching 180
200 when we are really severely
working out cardiac output
continues to increase but
after that threshold it
begins to fall it cannot
handle that the autonomic the
automatic regulation mechanism
is hit at a maximum and
then you are finding the
cardiac output decreasing
okay so here in this example
as the right atrial pressure
increases cardiac output
cardiac output in a normal
situation increases and it
flattens up after a certain
cardiac output okay beyond
when the sympathetic
stimulation increases as in
even pathological conditions
like heart failure that is
enhanced sympathetic stimulation
early on especially it
bumps up shoots up so high
or in parasympathetic
stimulation it shoots down it
goes down okay and then the
goal of what is the goal
now the main goal of all
these things is to maintain
the blood pressure Blood
pressure is the ultimate
thing to maintain and blood
pressure is the product
of cardiac output times
total peripheral resistance.
Ok,
these are some of the key
points. Remember,
we'll move on.
Frank-Starling's
Law. Alright, we are
getting into Frank
-Starling's Law.
What is it? It refers
to the preload. Frank
-Starling's Law states that
stroke volume increases
as ventricular EDV
increases. Before that,
why are we talking about
Frank-Starlings law?
Because preload is one of
the important factors that
regulate cardiac output.
Now we are entering into
the topic of what factors
regulate cardiac output.
One is preload, two
is afterload, three is
contractility, so we are
beginning with preload.
Preload refers to the
Frank-Starlings law, which
means it states that
stroke volume increases
as ventricular end
diastolic volume increases.
So, this is the pressure
volume loop, right,
back to PV loop, then
as the ventricular end
diastolic volume increases.
So, this was the original
end diastolic volume in
a normal patient. In an
unhealthy patient, in a
patient with, you know,
a diseased heart,
the end diastolic
volume increases and
reaches a new point,
okay. when this happens
the stroke volume increases
you see this was the stroke
volume normally now it
moves down to here so
stroke volume has increased
which means cardiac output
increases okay that is the
real point here so why does
that happen the passive
stretch of the ventricular
walls so the greater the
passive stretch of preload
of the ventricle the greater
the force of ventricular
contraction it's like
you push in so much blood
in an elastic or an elastic
balloon it tries to stretch
so similarly when heart
is receiving more blood
through the right atrium it
tries to push out more
blood that it has received
that's it that's Frank
Stodding's law moving on what
is venous vasoconstriction
contributes to increased
venous return and increased
ventricular stretch that
leads to enough force to
inject the extra return I
just explained that. And
only the EDV changes, ESV
does not change. And this
normally prevents the pooling
of the blood in pulmonary
circulation. Okay, so
we are balancing the
circulation by this mechanism.
This is Frank Starlingslaw.
And you need to remember this.
Starlink curves. So what
are Starlink curves?
Starlink curves refer to set
of curves. This is normal
Starlink curve okay in a
normal struggling curve the
black one dark black one
then when you're exercising
okay working out and the
curve goes to the left
which means as the pre
-load increases more and
more blood comes from the
you know your peripheral
uh you know from your
legs etc it goes up to
the heart and the stroke
volume increases why
does heart heartbeats
heartbeat increases at the
same time heart output
volume also increases.
So that is because of
this Frank Sterling's
law. Next time you
go and you're working
out, you can feel the
heartbeat, you can
feel the energy and
the blood is pumping.
That means your stroke
volume is increasing
and cardiac output
is also increasing.
Again heart rate is balancing
but at least the stroke
volume is increasing. But
in a patient with heart
failure, this is heart
failure curve, significantly
decreases, so the starlings
curve moves to the right.
Okay, so ventricular
volume increasing,
it is not generating
enough pressure
and it's not generating
enough volume.
So stroke volume doesn't
increase as much and even
though the preload increases.
Okay, but when you give
a drug such as digoxin or
there are numerous wonderful,
you know, positive inotropic
heart failure drugs,
drugs to improve heart
failure, improve the
contractility and so on. When
you do that, the curve shifts
to the left. Depending on
how efficacious the drug
is, it gets closer to the
normal or it at least tries
to reach there. Okay, so
this is Starlink's curve.
okay one more thing I
wanted to say in the in the
previous slide briefly here
it's important to note that
during diastole the heart
muscle rests and the coronary
blood flow to the sub
endocardial portions of the
left ventricle occurs
during diastole so then all
parts of the body receive
blood during ventricular
systole the heart itself the
heart muscle has to receive
some blood for its own
survival right that happens
when heart is in diastole
that's because the blood
coronary blood flow at the
at the cusps of the aortic
aortic cusp right adjusted
the origin of red ventricular
outflow tract it receives
in the sinuses and coronary
artery originates there
that receives blood during
ventricular diastole so
both phases are important
okay we cannot compromise.
All right, let's move on.
Afterload, what's
afterload? Afterload is the,
this is a next factor
regulating cardiac output.
Afterload is the arterial
pressure that the
heart muscle must overcome
to circulate breath.
Pause and reread that.
The greater the afterload,
the smaller the stroke volume.
Okay,
there, the greater the
preload, the greater the stroke
volume here the greater
the afterload the smaller
the stroke volume the decrease
in stroke volume causes
an increase in end systolic
volume so there we saw
end diastolic volume here
end systolic volume from
here it moves to here end
systolic volume okay increased
in systolic volume is
happening and the shortening
is reduced so the stroke
volume is decreasing so
hypertension is one scenario
where it can increase
the afterload and decrease
the stroke volume and thus
cardiac output so stroke
volume was here it has now
become here all right lot
of concepts so I'm moving
on you can please take time
to reread and understand
contractility is the next
important factor as an example
we can take epinephrine
when an epinephrine is
endogenously or injected in
a patient with severe allergy
take a patient with severe
allergy and you have to be
like it's a life-saving drug
they always carry the EpiPen
or the variants of it and
then suddenly it has to
be given what happens immediately
it goes into the system
and increases the contractility
how does it work a
lot of signaling pathways
are involved but let's talk
about physiology here it
increases the isotonic shortening
so the stroke volume which
was here it increases.
So it's an intrinsic
measure of cardiac
performance augmented
by factors like
epinephrine. We'll see
a little more here.
So what happens here?
When you increase the
contractility, it's
called increased inotropy.
Okay. In a normal is
the black one. Decreased
afterload means it increases
the stroke volume. And then
increased afterload means
it decreases the stroke
volume increased inotropy
means it increases the
stroke volume and then
decreased inotropy means
decreased stroke volume okay
so take your time and think
and you will understand
this course uh the whole
point is to understand the
concept what how does it
impact the stroke volume
how does it impact the end
systolic and end diastolic
volumes okay all right
going on contractility right
let's understand a little
bit more of the mechanism
of contractility you're
expected to understand this
all right calcium induced
calcium so initially what
happens when an action potential
starts action potential
right this is about the
lectures on electrical
conduction and you know whatnot
so depolarization initiates
the whole story and action
potential arrives and
it causes an increase in
cytoplasmic calcium this L
-type calcium channel through
that a calcium goes inside
this small amount of calcium
will activate release of
a larger amount of calcium
from the sarcoplasmic
reticulum boom it comes out
through the ryanidin receptor
right now this is called
calcium induced calcium
release so what does it say
after depolarization calcium
enters into the cytocardiomyoside
via L10 calcium channel
and calcium then activates
the rhinodin receptors
to and then this receptor
senses intracellular calcium
and triggers the calcium
release from the SR this
is the SR sarcoplasmic
reticulum to further increase
the calcium availability in
the cell so it increases
the calcium content in the
cell now this calcium will go
and activate the sarcomeres
we have sarcomeres right
here we have sarcomeres
and the sarcomeres will you
would have learned in the
histology topic of cardiac,
you know, heart in this
block. So the sarcomeres
will receive and the troponin
binds with the calcium
and it activates
contraction. Once the
contraction is over,
hits maximum, then the
calcium has to go back.
It's recycling,
efficient recycling. It's
an efficient recycling
system inside the heart.
Every beat this happens,
every single beat,
the calcium comes
out, calcium goes in,
calcium comes out,
calcium goes in. So
imagine how well, how much
it should be efficient
to make it to beat
perfectly, right.
CERCA is an important molecule.
Sarcoplasmic endoplasmic
reticulum calcium
ATPase is crucial in
returning back the,
returning back the
calcium. And what else?
Extracerellular fluid there
is calcium and there is SR
is two sources for calcium
that's the point here okay
and the return processor right
there is another molecule
sodium calcium exchanger the
um that's another molecule
involved in returning
back the calcium what does
it do how does it work so one
circa we already saw sodium
calcium exchanger uses
atp energy released by the
movement of one solute that
is three sodium down its
electrochemical gradient which
is into the cell in exchange
for one calcium out of the
cell this is uphill out
against the electrochemical
gradient right against
electrochemical gradient so
three sodium out one calcium
three sodium in excuse me
one calcium out against the
gradient in the presence of
ATP sodium calcium exchanger
takes out the calcium remember
calcium was here which
entered here so it has to
be taken out so this is way
where it goes out and a
large amount of calcium goes
back in okay this is something
you need to understand
we'll understand this for
even more with an example of a
drug but before that I want
you to just understand DPDT
remember DPDT we saw
isovolumetric relaxation in the
cardiac cycle we're just
connecting that here okay so
DPDT this will help us
understand some of the factors
governing the isovolumetric
relaxation right this period
extends from the remember
aortic second heart sound
to the crossover point
between the left ventricular
left atrial pressure okay
and the maximum negative rate
of pressure development
remember this is isovolumetric
contraction this is
isovolumetric relaxation and this
filled blue area right the
maximum negative rate of
pressure development which
refers to the iso-volumetric
relaxation rate is increased
when the rate of calcium
uptake into the sarcoplasmic
reticulum is enhanced
so when the then then the
calcium goes back in to
sarcoplasmic reticulum this
is the phase that's happening
this is when that happens
okay then iso-volumetric
relaxation happens calcium
is returning back okay
keeps on it returns back
all right so that's what i
wanted to take home from this
slide and there is i have
written some more explanations
in the bottom of the
slide you can read to
understand more but i think
this is the basic thing
that's enough i don't
want to go too much into
mechanisms at this stage
okay all right in heart
failure what happens in
a heart failure condition
the contractility is
reduced when we give
medications to treat like an
ancient drug like digoxin
classic example right
digoxin inhibits sodium
potassium ATPase that's another
important molecule we saw
sodium calcium exchanger
but there is also sodium
potassium ATPase what does
it do it exchanges so
potassium K potassium in sodium
out so normally potassium
goes in and sodium goes out
that's normal and it's
an ATP dependent process
against the electrochemical
gradient but sodium pump when
you give digoxin the
intracellular sodium increases
which means it inhibits it
inhibits normally sodium
goes out but when you give
digoxin it inhibits this
enzyme and it increases the
sodium concentration inside
which means it reduces the
potassium concentration
outside. Less potassium
enters inside and more sodium
enters inside. When more
sodium enters inside the
increase in intracellular
sodium slows down the sodium
calcium exchanger which
means it slows the sodium
calcium exchanger which increases
the intracellular calcium
ion concentration the
whole idea behind treating
heart failure is increasing
this calcium concentration
inside why if you increase
calcium concentration
inside there's more calcium
available to bind to troponin
and more contractility
that's the idea so more
calcium how do you do that
by increasing more sodium how
do you do more sodium increase
by blocking the sodium
potassium ATPase okay
i'll leave you here please
think and you will get it
all right so that's about
contractility let's move on
how do you actually measure
the whole heart's
functionality in practically in
clinical cardiology injection
fraction is readily measured
non-invasively using
ultrasound using outpatient
yeah and it's a it's it's a
it's a wonderful technique
You can see on the
top here, it's a
methodology that can
be used to measure.
You keep the probe at a
certain location on the
chest, transthoracically,
transesophageal is
also possible, but that's
a little more invasive,
but non-invasive is on
the top of the chest.
And with that, you can measure
end-diastolic dimension.
This is left ventricular
posterior wall, this
is left ventricular
anterior wall, this is
This is probably valve,
so you can ignore that.
And this is probably
intraventricular septum, or
the other side of the left
ventricular chamber. But
that's not important. Let's
talk about this region.
So here, this dimension
will help us measure
the end diastolic
volume. It will show.
Automatically it will output
these numbers. You see in
the bottom left ventricular
posterior wall diameter,
it shows, right? But
it will also show the
estimate by Simpsons
method, for instance,
and other methods we can
get left to end diastolic
volume. Don't worry
about those methods. Just
focus on the formula here.
End diastolic volume minus
left-traumatic end
systolic volume times 100
divided by EDV. So EDV minus
ESV, first do that number
calculation and then
times 100 divided by EDV.
EDV minus ESV is stroke
volume. Remember,
this stroke volume. you
may be given just stroke
volume or you may be given
edv you may be given ESV you
should be able to calculate
the this using this formula
what is ejection
fraction and then fractal
shortening is the same thing
except instead of volume these
numbers diastolic dimension
okay LVIDD or LVEDD
whatever it is called as same
thing F2 integral dimension
minus this is diastole
minus this is diastole by
diastole is fractional
shortening okay these are
clinically used parameters
to assess how well the heart
is pumping okay and this
just shows how it shows how
integrated the whole system
is how interacting it
is after load after load is
after load contract preload
all of them determine
myocardial fiber shortening
and that determines the
stroke volume we already
saw that stroke volume
times heart rate is cardiac
output. Cardiac output
times peripheral resistance
is RTL pressure. So it
just brings all of them
together in one chart.
And left ventricular size
increases is also impacting
the stroke volume.
Okay.
All right. And
increases the solid
line and decreases
the broken line.
Let's move on.
And just one note on
echocardiogram. Traditionally,
it's a big machine, but
nowadays handheld devices are
coming it's really cool
you can just have one small
handheld device and measure
these parameters you know
in ER for instance it's
even more convenient or even
in in trauma conditions even
in um war zones it can be
used when someone is really
affected immediately you
can check how good the
blood flow is it's not just
for the heart any vascular
blood flow can be measured,
you know, it's really
helpful in various conditions
and you can and people
are also using like
a stethoscope so future
of stethoscope we don't
know but I think it's
really a cool technology.
All right moving on in
the interest of time
I would let you work
on this Starling's
law. Pause, I'm going
to say the answer.
C is the answer, C
is in Charlie. Okay,
so let's move on.
Cardiac output, these are
variables like preload,
afterload, contractility.
Please take time to read. These
are self-explanatory, you know,
how do venous vasodilators
impact the preload, how
do arterial vasodilators
impact afterload. These are
some of the pharmacological
examples, which you will
study more in detail in
the pharmacology lectures.
It's just giving you context
here okay and CARD is the
acronym that impacts the
cardiac myocardialoxic demand
ejection fraction we already
saw in heart failure with
reduced ejection fraction
reduces heart failure with
preserved ejection fraction
it is preserved so even if
ejection fraction is normal
heart can mean heart
failure and that's another
whole big separate world
it's a newer thing it's more
recently discovered phenomena
that it's a bigger issue
and more tell model as well
case study okay we are getting
to the case study remember
in the first hour we saw
i introduced the case
briefly but let's look into
the case 73 year old man
visits the yard with complaints
of exceptional dyspnea syncope
chest pain hypercholesterolemia
11 year history of
hypertension bp is not
increased lungs are clear
systolic murmur loudest over
the aorta peaks at mid-systole
ECG ST segment is normal
left axis deviation large
left ventricle in the x
-ray calcified aortic valve
you know but observed
echocardiogram shows increased
velocity of flow through the
systolic portion of the
cardiac cycle left heart is
enlarged and left ventricular
hypertrophic cardiac enzymes
are normal which means
there is no possibility of
myocardial infarction so
going to the answer options
antihypertensive what is the
treatment option here the
question is oh where is the
question I think the question
probably is missing I
apologize for that so the
question is what is the
treatment your treatment option
is antihypertensive therapy
no because the pressures
are normal even though he
has history pressure pressure
is in fact on the little
on the lower end systolic
coronary artery bypass grafting
when do you do that? You
do it or even percutaneous
coronary intervention.
Whenever there is a heart
attack or unstable angina,
NSTEMI. NSTEMI is non-ST
elevated myocardial infarction.
So these are situations
where patients may
need one of these,
percutaneous coronary
intervention or coronary
artery bypass grafting.
Aortic valve replacement,
we'll come back to that.
Sublingual nitroglycerin,
again it's used for angina.
Angina is chest pain because
of ischemic heart disease.
In this case, it's a valve
problem. Why? You see there
is a systolic murmur,
there is a calification of
aortic valve, and there is,
and which means there is left
ventricular heart is
enlarged. Let's see if I have
another figure here. Yes, I
have a figure here. So, what
happens is, whenever there is
aortic valve is obstructed,
which means aortic valve
is closing here, it's not
able to close fully, and
because of that, there is a,
because of that,
the, I think the, the
pressure here significantly
will increase,
okay, it goes very high
so that's what happens and
because of that I don't have
more figures so because of
that there is the systolic
murmur you're hearing
loudest at the aorta at the
peak mid system right so
that means the treatment
that you need is aortic valve
either repair or replacement
depending on the patient
conditions okay I think
we're getting close to time
we'll move on so this is
summary we saw laplace we
saw pressure volume loops
we saw cardiac output we saw
stroke volume factors
regulating preload afterload
contractility and so on and
some pathological conditions
you can there are more
examples and I will give
some some sample questions
in the next few slides this
is a cool you know practice
TV loop so go to the site
and practice various
different scenarios clinical
questions with explanations
they explain so this is
important questions may come
using you know like with
this time and here you go
you have bunch of practice
sample questions from my own
collection that I've given
and then you have a
scholar Rx three different
scholar Rx links with questions
are available these are
detailed key studies there
you go so you have a bunch
of books here cases and
cancer books this is second
book third book they have
questions here as well so
login using inward id as
needed and start practicing
these are actual reference
books materials uh
recent books as well
scholar products as well
that's pretty much it um
i think that's all if you
have you know more
questions uh feel free to
email me i hope things have
been clear we saw we saw
various different concepts
so best wishes and
And we will see you in
another session, thank you.